Every time companies like Anthropic,
OpenAI, Gemini
They will release new LLM model
And they will claim they have the
world's best performing model
And they will show you these metrics
But if you observe clearly
The metric called MMLU is almost
same across all of these models
If that metric is almost same for
all
How are they comparing and saying
that our model is the best in the
world
And to know which is correct in this
I have gone through and read every
single research paper on topics like
MMLU, MMLU Pro, GPQA, SWE-Bench
Testing
Tool Testing, and many more
So that you don't need to read all
of these papers
So in this video we are going to
understand
Every single metric that is needed
to evaluate LLMs
After watching this video
You will never see the benchmarks of
the LLMs
Like the way you used to see before
And I will also explain
How to choose the best model for
your specific use case
So without any delay let's get
started
Before we understand how to evaluate
LLMs
Before we see the metrics
We will see what are all the common
mistakes
That people usually make while
choosing the LLM models
So the first mistake is
Thinking that the higher score is
better model
If you notice properly
For all the top models
Opus 4.8, ChatGPT 5.5,
DeepSeek V4, Gemini 3.5 Pro
For all of them
Almost MMLU score is 89 -92
%
Almost 1 -2 % difference
In that 1 -2 % difference
How are you going to evaluate which
model is better model
That is the first mistake
And the second mistake is
Trusting one benchmark
If you look at any of the latest LLM
releases
They have a sheet of metrics
It has different different metrics
That are evaluated on different
different types of things
They are called benchmarks
So some models are good at reasoning
Some models are very good at coding
Some models are very good at agentic
coding
Some models are very good at art
So not every single model is good at
every single thing
So that's why when you look at
benchmarks
We have different list of benchmarks
In that you need to choose
Which is the one which is applicable
for your use case
And the third one is the data
contamination
These LLMs are very popular for the
last 4 -5 years
So before that
They have created a lot of data sets
to evaluate these LLMs
In the last 4 -5 years
All that data is being fed to these
new models
That means the paper got leaked
And that is why these models can
score very high in the benchmarks
And sometimes they don't perform
well in the real time
And the last one which is the mixing
of different leaderboards
Because as we talked about
benchmarks
Different different models have
different different capabilities
Where they are good at
So according to that
They have different different
leaderboards
You cannot see at one leaderboard
and say
This model is good
You need to look at what is the
specific use case
Now for the actual LLM evaluation
There are three different types of
techniques that usually market
follows
One is the typical benchmarks
You can think of them like a board
exams
They are specific set of data sets
They will try to evaluate on those
data sets
How well the large language model is
performing
In that
Some different metrics are
MMLU, MMLU Pro, SWE
Bench, GPQA Diamond and Frontier
Math
Now let's go ahead and understand
what is it
So what is the first thing
MMLU
MMLU means measuring massive
multitask language understanding
So what they do in this
They will try to evaluate
Performance in our large language
model
Across different different type of
domains
Let's say like this
Abstract algebra, anatomy,
astronomy, business ethics,
clinical knowledge
College biology, chemistry,
computer science, mathematics,
physics
I mean this is like a generalized
question and answers
In different different domains
In all those domains
How our LLM model performs
There are so many different domains
You don't need to go through all of
these things
And based on that
They will give you how much accurate
the LLM answers in all of these
questions
That is what a simple thing
And another thing is
MMLU Pro
MMLU Pro is based on different
domains
They create even harder questions
So they can evaluate even better
So if you look at MMLU and MMLU Pro
Always lean towards the number which
is better in the MMLU Pro
First thing
And let's look at the second thing
Which is called Chatbot Arena
What is this Chatbot Arena
It is a website that is built by
humans
Where LLMs are there
They will ask questions
They will answer
They will say whether the answer is
correct
People will evaluate
People like us
Not the companies who built these
LLMs
That is what we have something
called as Chatbot Arena
Usually compared to our leaderboard
Chatbot Arena benchmarks are much
better
Because these benchmarks are derived
based on the user's preference
Based on our user's preference
Human preference data collection
Pair wise comparison to rankings
There are so many things that they
have did this
And Chatbot Arena is usually the
better option
And another thing is terminal bench
Terminal bench is
How well the LLM is good at
understanding and doing tasks via
command line interface
Command line interface is basically
You are talking to your machine via
commands
So there are terminals in our
laptops
And almost every single thing that
you can do on your machine
Can be done via terminals
You can talk via CLI through command
line interface
You can talk to AWS
You can talk to Github
You can talk to internet via CLI
So what works well in CLI
The LLM is working very good at
executing tasks
By doing a lot of other stuff
So this is a paper
They will also evaluate how good the
LLM is in these tasks
Terminal bench
If you go through this paper
See how it performs in GPT 5.2 Codex
Claude
Resolution rate
Opus 4.5
Gemini 3.0
And Gemini 3 flash
GPT 5
Kimi K2 instruction model
So there are a lot of people who are
doing these evaluations for us
So that we can specifically rely on
which model is doing it
Which task
And the next paper which is called
GPQA
This GPQA is
It is like
Let's say there is a Google
professor
He is doing PhD
For such PhD graduate level
professors
You give questions and answers
If you give such questions,
what kind of answers will you give
In the same way
By preparing a different set of
questions and answers
And that are at a level of graduate
level Google professors
They will evaluate
And the LLMs how they are answering
If they answer correctly or if they
answer well
By evaluating
They will give us a score
See
Question writing and expert
validation
Non -expert validation
And after doing all this
They will give the score for these
questions
So whichever model performs well in
this
Those are very good at research
level
You can look at Opus 4.8
And mythos
The recent model Fable 5
They are very good at GPQA
And that is why they are very good
at research power
And then next we have something
which is called as
Large language models evaluation on
a trained code
What they do is
Taking multiple production level
GitHub repos
How our LLMs maintain those repos
Whether these LLMs are building new
stuff
Are they correctly pushing the code
How are they handling merge requests
Are they deploying the code or not
They test all of this live on a
production GitHub code
So even that is also being
calculated
While evaluating LLMs
And one more
Software engineering bench
How software engineering development
is done
And one more paper
Stable tool bench
How tools are used more
And then next training verifies
To solve math real world problems
How real world math problems are
solved
There are so many things where
These LLMs are being evaluated to
That is why
Taking only one metric
And saying that this metric is good
You need to look at different
different metrics
And then the next one which is
called
Human evolution
Of course we all know
Once the LLMs are released
We all use them
And we will give a review as well
Yes or no
Whether they are good or not
That is what human evolution is
In that chartbot arena is one of the
top
And there are 6.8 million plus votes
And it is open source to all the
people
Based on the model that we like
And this is a real world test
And these cannot be faked
And the third one which is
LLM as a judge
You have built an LLM
To evaluate that LLM
You use one more LLM
So in that you have different
different
Types of techniques
Which are like G avalani
Deep avalani
Ragaas
Custom rubiks
There are so many
But these are
One by one
Actually
When we build an LLM
If another LLM is already judged
That should be even more powerful
But who evaluated that powerful
model
We don't know
So there are so many things that
Can be done while evaluating LLMs
Not just one
So when you go via benchmarks
What is this
These can be faked
And it is not too reliable these
days
And when you go via human evolutions
Overall the best quality I would say
And when you go via LLM as a judge
You can use for a specific use case
If you want quick and faster results
Till now we have learned
All the different metrics
Let's look at it in a single glance
What is MMLU
They test on general knowledge
And almost 92 % of all
Achieved
And MMLU pro
Harder version than MMLU
10 multiple choice for every
question
And it is still relevant right now
It is not yet saturated
And software engineering bench
On real github issues
This is not saturated
Even if you look at the latest
models
They are still getting better
At agentic coding
And GPQA
This is basically
PHD level science
This is not yet saturated
Because we still see some models
Which are approximately at 65 %
There is a lot of scope
To learn for these LLMs
And frontier math is not yet
saturated
We still have
Less than 80 % results
Only for the latest models
And humanity's last exam
What is this
Like our AI, like our robo cinema
They have all the ethics
Psychological values
And all that stuff
That is what at least
Humanity's last exam
And it is not yet saturated
And chatbot arena
Which is also really good one
Now you will say
How to remember all these names
It is very hard to understand and
remember these things
That is why
What I have done is
I have classified all of these
results
Into the exams that we got used to
So MMLU
Is for 10th class exams
Everyone is almost passing
And MMLU pro
Is for 12th class exams
Everyone is going to pass
But little bit hard
And then GPQI
Is for gate exams
It is a bit difficult
To crack this exam
And then SWE Bench
Is for
After completing your education
You joined an internship
And the work you do there is
difficult
And then arena LO
Is basically job interview
And Frontier Math test
Is the IITJ
Advanced exam
Hopefully
With the names of these exams
You will remember the names of LLM
Evaluation Metrics
And the next part is LLM as a judge
There are three different modes
First mode is
Single Output Scoring
You have a question
That question is answered by
Rag chatbot
And then the answer is
As a judge
Whether this answer contains
The information for the given
question
Or not
You can put the rating
That is first thing
And second thing is
Pair wise comparison
You have multiple answers
They are given to the judge
The judge will evaluate
Which answer worked better
These multiple answers
Will give multiple models
That is what we call it as a pair
wise
Comparison
Comparing two models how arena works
And then the third one is
Reference based grading
So let's say
We got an LLM answer
But for the same question
We already have a gold standard
answer
The typical answer
By comparing those two
You give a score
This is what we call it as a
reference based
So in LLM as a judge
People usually use these three
different techniques
And then we have
Bias
When using LLM as a judge
Our judge already
Has more talent in some games
So let's say
When we are using a judge
The judge is already very good at
Software engineering
So when the results are
On software engineering
He might not be giving
The actual ones
So there are
Different different biases
Which is position bias
Prefers whichever answer
It reads first
And second is verbosity bias
And third is
Self preference bias
And the fourth is authority bias
What are these biases?
Our judge
LLM judge
Is a personality
Some people are angry
Some are loving
Some are kind
And our LLM judge
Is a personality
Because of that personality
The LLM we evaluate
The answers change
That is what we have in the bias
section of LLMs
And then the next one
Which is called
Why benchmarks lie
Now we have seen all these numbers
We have understood all these numbers
But we can believe these numbers
That is where the last step
Will come into picture
No, because
Now there is MMLU
All the questions in MMLU are known
to everyone
Now what they will do
They will feed these questions to
the model itself
So the model button is already stuck
So when we test them
They will get better results
So data contamination
Is always happening
And you cannot blindly trust the
benchmarks
And second thing is
Saturation
Every model
Scores 90 plus in MMLU
Then what is the point of this exact
metric?
And the third one is
Benchmark hacking
So now these benchmarks are there
The companies know
So they will train their models
To ace these benchmarks
Not for general tasks
So you are just like hacking into
The benchmark leaderboard
So even that thing will happen
And the fourth one is the vibes
problem
Or the bias problem
So by eliminating all these
To get the better one
The three layer approach
One is you shortlist the models
Based on benchmarks
And you go to the arena
And compare which one is better
From the audience perspective
And third you design your own
Evaluation metrics and decide which
LLM is best for you
That is how you will do the
Evaluation for these LLMs
And the last slide is
How to actually pick a model
That is best for your use case
So what should we do first?
Define what is the capability
You need, how much performance you
need
Do you want a coding model?
Do you want a reasoning model?
Or do you want to work well in art?
To be good in physics?
It depends on your use case
Then based on your use case
Shortlist three to five different
models
From these benchmarks
After that, you go and check
In the arena website
Whether they are in the top
leaderboard
And after that
Run LLM as a judge on your own data
Execute on your own data
And you pick the one which is better
Performing across all of these
things
So that is how you will
Understand how the LLM
Evaluation works and how to
Choose the best LLM based on your
use case
But not relying
Purely on these benchmarks
In this video
I hope you learned something
From this video
And if you have learned something
Please let me know what is the topic
That you learned best in this video
And share it with the one who might
need this video
That's all for this one
Bye bye